A Guide to the Minutes of the Virginia House of Delegates, 1776-1860, 1900-1977.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Minutes of the Virginia House of Delegates,
1776-1860, 1900-1977.
The Library of Virginia
25579, 27646, 28146, 35166, 35167, 35168, 35169, 37566
Virginia. General Assembly. House of Delegates.
91 v.
Administrative Information
Arranged chronologically.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions
Acquisition Information
Accession 35166 was transferred prior to 1905.
Historical Information
The House of Delegates' predecessor, the House of Burgesses, was modeled after the House of Commons, in Parliament. The House of Burgesses existed from 1643 to 1776. The first session of the General Assembly, which took place in 1776, established the first constitution and made the House of Delegates the most powerful branch in state government. It was not until the constitution of 1851 was adopted that a more equitable balance among the branches of government was established. In the General Assembly, members of the House of Delegates and the Senate vote on legislation entered during the legislative session. Legislative bills can originate either in the House of Delegates or in the Senate, with both chambers having the ability to establish study committees. Each serves as a check upon the other to ensure a thorough debate on the merits of each bill.
Scope and Content
These minute books document the daily recording of House of Delegates proceedings. They include order of business; bills and resolutions introduced or acted upon; notations of correspondence, reports, and petitions read; ballots counted; appointments; and additional summaries of legislative action. The library has minute books for 1776-1860, 1900-1973 and 1975-1977. Volumes are also referred to as Order books.
Contents List
- Minute books of the Virginia House of Delegates, 1776-1860, 1900-1977.
  - Accession 35166 (1776-1860)., Extent: xx v.
    Minute book, 1776 May-1777 June 28, includes Convention of Delegates, 1776 May 6-July 5.
    Manay of the Minute books, 1777-1817, include lists of delegates for sessions.
    Minute book, 1777 Oct 20-1778 Dec 9, also includes Lists of delegates by committee, 1778 May 4 and 1778 Oct 7.
    Minute book, 1782 Oct 12-Dec 28 also includes a typed transcript for 1782 Oct 21-Dec 28.
    Minute book, 1790 Oct 20-1794 Dec 25, includes Standing orders of the House of Delegates, undated.
    The majority of the Minutes books, 1798, 1803-1836, include lists of laws passed during the session.
    - Minute book, 1776 May 6-1777 June 28. (Box 1)
    - Minute book, 1777 Oct 20-1778 Dec 9 [1777 Oct 20-1778 Jan 24; 1778 May 13-June 1; 1778 Oct 5-Dec 9]. (Box 2)
    - Minute book, 1780 May 1-1781 Mar 22 [1780 May 1-July 14; 1780 Oct 16-1781 Jan 2; 1781 Mar 1-22]. (Box 2)
    - Minute book, 1781 Oct 1-1783 Dec 22 [1781 Oct 1-3; 1781 Nov 5-1782 Jan 5; 1782 May 6-July 2; 1782 Oct 21-Dec 28; 1783 May 5-June 28; 1783 Oct 20-Dec 22]. (Box 2)
    - Minute book, 1784 May 3-1787 Jan 11 [1784 May 3-June 30; 1784 Oct 18-1785 Jan 7; 1785 Oct 17-1786 Jan 21; 1786 Oct 16-1787 Jan 11]. (Box 3)
    - Minute book, 1787 Oct 15-1788 Jan 8; 1795 Nov 20-Dec 29. (Box 3)
    - Minute book, 1788 June 23-Dec 30 [1788 June 23-30; 1788 Oct 20-Dec 30]. (Box 3)
    - Minute book, 1790 Oct 20-1794 Dec 25 [1790 Oct 20-Dec 29; 1791 Oct 19-Dec 19; 1792 Oct 2-Dec 27; 1793 Oct 23-Dec 11; 1794 Nov 12-Dec 25]. (Box 5)
    - Minute book, 1795 Nov 30-1799 Jan 23 [1795 Nov 30-Dec 20; 1796 Nov 8-Dec 26; 1797 Dec 18-1798 Jan 25; 1798 Dec 6-1799 Jan 23]. (Box 5)
    - Minute book, 1799 Dec 4-1802 Feb 2. (Box 5)
    - Minute book, 1802 Dec 8-1809 Feb 16. (Box 5)
    - Minute book, 1791 Oct 17-Dec 20 (Box 6)
    - Minute book, 1791 Oct 1-Dec 28. (Box 6)
    - Minute book, 1793 Oct 21-Dec 13. (Box 6)
    - Minute book, 1796 Nov 8-1798 Jan 28 [1796 Nov 8-Dec 27; 1797 Dec 4-1798 Jan 28]. (Box 6)
    - Minute book, 1798 Dec 3-1799 Jan 26. (Box 7)
    - Minute book, 1799 Dec 2-1801 Jan 15 [1799 Dec 2-1800 Jan 28; 1800 Dec 1-1801 Jan 15. (Box 7)
    - Minute book, 1801 Jan 15-1802 Feb 2 [1801 Jan 15-23; 1800 Dec 1-1801 Jan 15. (Box 7)
    - Minute book, 1802 Dec 6-1803 Jan 29. (Box 7)
    - Minute book, 1803 Dec 5-1805 Feb 1 [1803 Dec 5-1804 Feb 3; 1804 Dec 3-1805 Feb 1]. (Box 8)
    - Minute book, 1805 Dec 2-1806 Feb 6. (Box 8)
    - Minute book, 1806 Dec 1-1808 Feb 10 [1806 Dec 1-1807 Jan 22; 1807 Dec 7-1808 Feb 10]. (Box 8)
    - Minute book, 1810 Dec 3-1811 Feb 14. (Box 9)
    - Minute book, 1811 Dec 2-1812 Feb 21. (Box 9)
    - Minute book, 1812 Nov 30-1813 May 26. (Box 10)
    - Minute book, 1813 Dec 6-1814 Feb 16. (Box 10)
    - Minute book, 1817 Dec 1-1818 Feb 26. (Box 11)
    - Minute book, 1818 Dec 18-1819 Mar 13. (Box 12)
    - Minute book, 1819 Dec 6-1820 Feb 25. (Box 13)
    - Minute book, 1820 Dec 4-1821 Mar 6. (Box 14)
    - Minute book, 1821 Dec 3-1822 Mar 4. (Box 14)
    - Minute book, 1822 Dec 2-1823 Feb 25. (Box 15)
    - Minute book, 1823 Dec 1-1824 Mar 10. (Box 15)
    - Minute book, 1826 Dec 4-1827 Mar 9. (Box 16)
    - Minute book, 1828 Dec 1-1829 Feb 28. (Box 16)
    - Minute book, 1829 Dec 7-1831 Apr 19 [1829 Dec 7-1830 Feb 23; 1831 Apr 7-19]. (Box 17)
    - Minute book, 1832 Dec 3-1833 Mar 9. (Box 17)
    - Minute book, 1833 Dec 12-1834 Mar 14. (Box 18)
    - Minute book, 1834 Dec 1-1835 Mar 12. (Box 18)
    - Minute book, 1835 Dec 7-1836 Mar 24. (Box 18)